（いの）まったく！　だいたい
デリカシーってものがないのよ！
Damn it!
He's so insensitive!
Hey, come on.
（シカマル）おいおい
忍界大戦が始まろうってのに→
Should you be fighting
with your dad
when the Great Ninja War's
about to start?
親子喧嘩してる場合かよ。
（いの）だって…。
But...
((いのいち：いの…　入る…。
I'm coming in, Ino.
キャ～！
（いのいち）うわ～っ！
You're so stupid, Dad!
（いの）父さんのバカ～！
で　何の用よ。
So, what do you want?
いや　その…　ここんとこ
ふさいでいただろ？
Well, you seem so
preoccupied lately.
So I was wondering...
だから…　父さんでよければ
相談に乗るぞ。
if you wanted to,
you could talk to me.
別に何でもないわよ。
There's nothing.
お前の悩み　わからんでもない。
I'm not completely clueless
to what you're going through.
いのも　年頃だしな。
なによ　それ。
You're a young woman now.
What's that supposed to mean?
どっちに決めたんだ？
はぁ？
So which one did you pick?
(いや…　シカマルとチョウジ
どっちと　つきあうつもりだ？))
So is it Shikamaru or Choji?
Who did you decide
to go out with?
Why should I go out
with you guys?
なんで　私が　あんたたちと
つきあわなきゃならないわけ！？
そもそも　レディーの部屋を
ノックもなしに入ってくるなんて→
And most of all,
he has the nerve to enter
a lady's room without knocking first!
どういう神経してるわけ～？
（シカマル）おい　いの。
Hey, why are you
taking it out on us?
なんで　俺たちが
文句言われなきゃなんねえんだ。
Calm down.
（チョウジ）まぁまぁ。　いのいちさんも
いののことが心配なんだよ。
Inoichi is just worried about you.
しかしよ　サスケのことで→
Remember,
you did cry a lot over Sasuke.
泣きべそかいていたのは
本当だしな。
So he's not far off the mark.
当たらずも遠からずって
感じじゃねえか？
あ…　あれは
急に言われたからよ。
That's because it
happened so suddenly.
それに　サスケ君のことは
私が悩んだって　しようがない。
Besides, worrying about Sasuke
isn't going to do any good.
もう　サクラたちに
任せることに決めたのよ。
I've decided to leave it
to Sakura and her team.
《へぇ　吹っ切れたみたいだな。
Well, it seems Ino's over it.
対戦を前にして　心がブレてちゃ
連係もうまくいかねえ。
With war looming,
our teamwork would have suffered
if she wasn't focused.
(いのは大丈夫だな))
I guess Ino's going to be okay.
おい　チョウジ　おめえは…。
お前が悪いんだろ！
Hey, Choji, are you...
You're to blame!
お前のほうが　先に手を出した！
（シカマル）お…　おい！
You started it!
H-Hey!
You're the one who
complained first!
文句言ったのは　お前が先じゃん！
（チョウジ）やめなよ。　いったい
何があったっていうのさ。
Stop it!
Just what is going on here?
兄ちゃんには関係ないぜ！
この　デ…。
Stay out of this, you fat—
か　体が…　勝手に…。
My body is moving on its own!
影真似の術　成功。
Shadow Possession Jutsu
complete.
里がこんな状態なのに
喧嘩なんかしてちゃ駄目でしょ。
You shouldn't be fighting
when the village is in
the situation that it is...
But he...
だって　こいつが…。
だってじゃないの。
No "buts"!
You'll never be popular
with the girls
細かいこと言ってると→
if you argue over small things.
女の子に　モテないわよ。
（３人）う　うん…。
– O-Okay.
じゃあ　あっち行って
仲よく遊んでなさい。
Now go over there
and play nicely.
– Okay.
（３人）は～い！
As usual,
that was perfect teamwork.
（コスケ）相変わらず
見事な連係ですなぁ。
（いの）あなた　たしか…。
Aren't you?
Umm... who is he?
えっと　誰だっけ？
コスケさん…　だったよな？
Kosuke, right?
He's been a genin for fifty years.
下忍一筋５０年　木ノ葉最強の
下忍とも言われる　コスケさんだよ。
Kosuke is also known as
the Hidden Leaf's strongest genin.
前にも会ってるじゃねえか。
そうだったかなぁ？
We've met him before.
Really?
あっ！　僕らが　まだ下忍の頃に！
Oh yeah!
When we were still genin.
（コスケ）はい。　いつぞやは
お世話になりましたなぁ。
Yes. I was much obliged
to you back then!
ibitsu na merodll de dekita aisareru beki ikimono da
Made from a distorted melody,
I'm a creature that should be loved
seika wa agerarenakute mo kokoro ga utatte iru kara
Even if I can't better myself,
I'll continue to sing from my heart
dore dake tsuyoi ame koete aisareru beki ikimono ka?
What storms must I overcome
To be a creature who should be loved?
yakusoku ga mamorenakute mo kokoro wa utatte iru kedo
Even if you can't keep your promise
My heart will keep on singing, but...
dono doa nokku shite aketara ii?
Which door should I knock on and open?
aketara doko e mukattara ii?
Once I open it, where should I go?
hitori ja kaerenai kara
I can't go home by myself
dareka o matte ita dake
I was just waiting for someone
kimi ga ima ichiban aitai hito wa dare?
Who is the one you want to meet the most?
kokoro no naka de dake hanaseru hito no kazu wa fuete iku
The number of people that I can only speak to in my heart
keep increasing
dakara tsuyoku naritakatta tada
So I just wanted to be strong
bokura mada yomitarinai monogatari
Our story just hasn't been told enough
muriyari owarenai koto wakattete
We know it's not something we can just quit
dare mo mina jibun no mama
Because we all want to be ourselves
tsuyoku naritakatta kara
We wanted to be strong
The Legendary Ino-Shika-Cho Trio
((この情報で　里の仲間が
危険に合わなくて済むのなら→
If this intel will spare
my comrades in the village from danger
わしの命なんぞ　安いもの。
I will gladly give up my life.
I must do everything I can
この巻物　なんとしても
木ノ葉へ届けなければ…。
to deliver this scroll
to the Hidden Leaf.
I won't let you escape!
逃がすか！
（岩狂）我ら三兄弟に追われて
逃げ切った者などおらん。
No one has ever escaped
the clutches of the three brothers.
（岩造）逃がさねえぜ。
We won't let you get away.
（岩次）兄者　追わないのか？
Big Brother,
aren't we going after him?
フフ…　おもしろいじじいだ。
What an interesting old man.
岩次　岩造
ありゃあ　変わり身だぜ。
Iwaji, Iwazo...
That's just a Substitution.
《チッ　目のいいやつめ》
He has sharp eyes.
（岩造）ナメるなよ　じじい！
Don't underestimate me,
old man.
《コスケ：足も　なかなか…》
He's fast too.
逃がすか！　土遁　大地合掌！
We won't let you go!
Earth Style: Earth Hold!
（岩次）逃がさねえって言っただろ。
I said, we won't let you escape!
《力も　なかなか…》
He has considerable strength too.
じじい　手間をかけやがって。
You're wasting my time, old man!
（岩狂）一人で　我らから
情報を盗み出そうなんて→
Trying to steal intel from
the three of us, huh?
逆に　おめえらの里の情報を
たっぷりと聞かせてもらうぜ。
Well, we'll return the favor
and make you tell us
everything about your village.
《相手にとって　不足なし。
My enemy has
no vulnerabilities.
I guess my life will end
on this moonlit night.
我が生涯果てるには
よい月夜か…》
（チョウジ）ゴ～ロゴロゴロ…。
新手か！？
Reinforcements?
（チョウジ）ゴロロン！　ゴロロン！　ゴロロン！
ゴロゴロゴロッ　ド～ン！
なんだ！？
か　体が勝手に！
What is that?!
My body just...
《影真似の術　成功！》
Shadow Possession Jutsu...
complete!
いの！
心転身の術！
Ino!
Mind Transfer Jutsu!
お前ら　ふざけてる場合じゃねえ！
Hey! This is not the time
to joke around.
よくも　木ノ葉の仲間を
やってくれたわね！
You men have some nerve
attacking our comrade
from the Hidden Leaf!
（２人）わね！？
"You men?"
フフン！　た～っぷり
お返しさせてもらうわ！
Well, it's payback time!
う　裏切ったのか！？　兄者。
おめえもだろうが！
Are you turning on us,
Big Brother?
You too?!
覚悟しなさ～い！
Get ready!
ほほう！　こ　これは…。
O-Oh, if it isn't...
（アスマ）終わりだ。
It's over.
（アスマ）術を解いてもいいぞ　いの。
You can release your jutsu, Ino.
何がどうなってるんだ？
What the hell is going on?
（チョウジ）これぞ　木ノ葉秘伝→
This is the Hidden Leaf's Secret
coordinated ninjutsu formation...
忍術の連係フォーメーション
猪鹿蝶だ～！
Ino-Shika-Cho!
ひぃっ！
All right! Mission accomplished!
よし　任務完了だ。
お前らは　今日のフォーメーションは
よかったぞ。
Your formation today
was spot on, guys!
修業の成果が出たな。
Your training is paying off.
（シカマル）あ？
（シカマル）大丈夫っすか？
いくらなんでも→
Are you all right?
Whatever the reason,
単独任務なんて　むちゃっすよ。
going off on a solo mission
is too reckless.
(フォーメーション猪鹿蝶に
二度も命を助けられるとは…))
I never expected to be rescued twice
by the Ino-Shika-Cho formation.
そうそう　下忍の頃に
僕らが救出した　コスケさんだ。
That's right.
You're Kosuke, the person we
rescued back when we were genin.
はい。　思い出して
いただいたようで→
Yes. I'm very happy
you remembered.
嬉しく思いますよ。
俺も思い出したんっすけど→
I just remembered too, but...
あの時
変なこと言ってましたよね？
You said something
interesting back then.
You said you had been saved twice
by Ino-Shika-Cho's formation.
確か　「フォーメーション猪鹿蝶に
二度助けられた」って。
（チョウジ）助けたことあったっけ？
さぁ…。
Did we rescue him twice?
I'm not sure.
私は　二度命を救われました→
My life was saved twice
by Ino-Shika-Cho.
フォーメーション猪鹿蝶にね…。
そう　あれは
木ノ葉崩しの前日のこと…。
Yes.
It was the day before the destruction
of the Hidden Leaf Village.
（コスケ）夜更けだというのに
翌日の祭りに→
It was late at night,
but the village was
abuzz with excitement
里は　ざわついておりました。
for the next day's festivities.
（ヒルゼン）よい匂いじゃな　コスケ。
That smells delicious, Kosuke.
邪魔だったかな？
Am I intruding?
じじいの鍋でよろしければ
ひとついかがですか　三代目様。
If you don't mind a hotpot stew
made by an old man,
please join me, Lord Third.
すまぬの。
With pleasure.
いよいよ明日は
中忍試験の本線ですな。
Tomorrow is the main portion
of the Chunin Exam.
ああ　そうじゃな。
Yes, that's right.
うまい。
It's so delicious!
ハハッ　こんなものばかり
達者になりましてな。
I'm only good at things like this.
なに　任務中の唯一の楽しみは
飯を食うことのみ。
What are you saying?
The only enjoyable part of a mission
is sitting down to eat.
おぬしを小隊のメンバーにと指名して
くる者も少なくないのだぞ。
Many specifically request you
to be on their team.
どのような危険な任務で
あろうとも　仰せとあらば。
No matter how risky the mission,
if you so order me...
そう命を粗末にするでない。
Do not take your life so lightly.
馳走になったな。
実にうまい一杯であった。
Thank you for the food.
It was mighty delicious.
By the way, Kosuke...
そうじゃ　コスケ。
ひとつ任務を頼まれてくれんか。
Will you accept one mission?
中忍試験が
各里のパワーバランスを見る機会ゆえ→
The Chunin Exam is
an opportunity to check
the power balance
between the villages,
多少　きな臭くなるのは
常なのじゃが。
so some mutual distrust
is to be expected.
ちと　今回は胸騒ぎしての。
But I just feel so uneasy this time.
まぁ　わしの早とちりなら
いいのだが。
Hopefully,
it's just my imagination.
A message from
the Third Hokage?
（チョウザ）三代目からの言づけだと？
チョウザ。
（シカク）声がでかい。
Choza!
Not so loud!
S-Sorry!
すまん。
で　火影様はなんと？
So what did Lord Hokage say?
木ノ葉舞う季節にはまだ早い。
こう伝えればわかると。
It is too early in the season for
the leaves to be dancing in the air.
He said you would understand.
言づけ承った。
Message received.
《猿飛一族と三家の特別暗号か》
A special code
between Sarutobi Clan
and their three houses, huh?
まさか！
Impossible?!
キャ～ッ。
Leaf Ninja Art!
木ノ葉流。
グワッ。
柳。
Yanagi!
Which enemy
infiltrated the village?
いったいどれほどの敵が
里に侵入したというのだ。
倍化の術。
Expansion Jutsu!
体が。
M-My body...
Is this your first encounter with
the Hidden Leaf's Secret...
木ノ葉秘伝
影縛りの術は初めてか？
Shadow Paralysis Jutsu?
じゃあ　ついでにくらえ。
木ノ葉秘伝　影首縛りの術。
Then take this one too!
The Hidden Leaf's Secret...
Shadow Strangle Jutsu!
心乱身の術！
Mind Destruction Jutsu.
（２人）うわっ！
やめろ！　どうした！？
か…　体が勝手に。
Stop! What's wrong?!
I can't control my body!
うわぁ！
昔を思い出すな。
This brings back old memories!
It's a reunion of
the Ino-Shika-Cho Trio.
猪鹿蝶トリオの再結集だな。
私とて　木ノ葉の忍。
I am also a shinobi
of the Hidden Leaf.
微力ながらも　この身
木ノ葉のために捧げますぞ！
I may not be skilled,
but I will gladly give up my life
for the sake of the village.
これ以上　木ノ葉をやらせん！
I won't allow you to ravage
the Hidden Leaf Village any further!
この老いぼれの身と引き換えに→
I will sacrifice this old body,
and take as many fools
as I can with me!
１人でも多くの愚か者を
葬ってくれる！
コスケさん。
Kosuke...
敵の中に飛び込んでいったのか。
He charged right into the enemy.
ほっとくのか？　シカク。
あれをやるぞ。
Are you going to
let him go, Shikaku?
Let's do it!
猪鹿蝶のフォーメーションか？
You mean,
the Ino-Shika-Cho Formation?
忘れたちゃおらんだろうな？
I hope you haven't forgotten it.
フン…　それを忘れちまうようじゃ
誓いのピアスが泣くぜ。
If I forgot it,
I don't deserve to wear the earring that
represents our oath of brotherhood!
フフッ。
だな。
That's true.
行くぞ！
おう！
Let's do it!
All right!
うおぉ～！
♪～
（シカク）相変わらず　いい影だぜ。
You always make
good shadows for me.
♪～
１０…　２０…。
Ten... twenty...
３３。
Thirty-three...
影縫いの術！
Shadow Stitching Jutsu!
♪～
（シカク）黒彼岸花。
Black Spider Lily!
トドメは頼んだぜ。
Deliver the finishing blow.
心乱演武の術！
Mind Destruction Dance Jutsu!
まったく　お前たちとだけは
戦いたくねえよ。
Damn it.
I never want to face
you guys in a fight.
おっと　そうだった。
Oh, that's right.
うわぁ…。
大丈夫かい？　コスケさん。
Are you all right, Kosuke?
さあて　次のエリアに行くぞ。
Now then...
Let's move on to the next area!
シカク　いのいち。
Shikaku, Inoichi.
あれこそ　木ノ葉の秘伝忍術による
最強フォーメーション→
As expected of the Hidden Leaf's
most powerful
Secret Ninjutsu Formation,
Ino-Shika-Cho!
猪鹿蝶。
うむ。
Uh-huh!
猪鹿蝶。
Ino... Shika... Cho...
心乱身の術！
Mind Destruction Jutsu!
影縛りの術。
Shadow Paralysis Jutsu!
倍化の術！
Expansion Jutsu!
♪～
なんという…
敵を圧倒しながら→
The way you battle
has such depth.
味方を勇気づける
懐の深さを持った戦い。
You overwhelm your opponents while
instilling courage in your comrades.
恐怖を仲間の勇気に変える
見事なフォーメーション。
A splendid formation that transforms
your comrades' fears into bravery.
経験力と判断力
そして何より信頼の力。
The power of your experience,
judgment and most of all, your faith
お見事でございます。
is magnificent!
そんなんじゃないんですよ
コスケさん。
It's nothing like that, Kosuke.
信頼も何も　腐れ縁ってだけで。
We're just stuck with each other,
whether we like it or not.
そうそう　ここだけの話
俺たちゃ自分のガキがいる里で→
Yeah, yeah. Don't tell anyone.
We just don't want to look bad
in the front of our kids
かっこ悪いとこは
見せられないってだけで。　なぁ。
since we all live in
the same village. Right?
はぁ？
Huh?
ま　それに俺たちなんて
あいつらは→
Well, in any case, our kids will
surpass us in no time at all.
あっという間に
追い抜いていきますよ。
木ノ葉の芽は
確実に育っていますからね。
The seedlings of
the Hidden Leaf Village
are growing soundly.
♪～
また生き延びてしまったか。
I survived once again... huh?
じゃが…。
Anyway...
木ノ葉の芽が
どんな大樹になっていくか→
it's going to be such a pleasure
to watch the seedlings of the Leaf
楽しみですな。
grow into giant trees.
（チョウジ）
父ちゃんたちが　そんな戦いを？
Our dads fought a battle like that?
やっぱり　すごいのね
父さんたち。
Our dads are amazing.
まいったな。
And here, I thought our formation
had gotten much better.
俺たちのフォーメーションも
レベルアップしてると思っていたが。
父さんたちのフォーメーションに比べたら
まだまだね。
Compared to our dads,
we still have a ways to go.
私が言うのもなんですが
忍は一日にして成らずですな。
If you don't mind my saying,
a shinobi isn't made in a day.
大樹になったときの
フォーメーション猪鹿蝶→
I look forward to
your Ino-Shika-Cho formation
楽しみにしていますよ。
when you have reached maturity.
おっと…　また助けてもらうことに
ならぬよう→
I should be more careful,
so you don't have to
come to my rescue again.
気をつけねばなりませんなぁ　ハハハ。
ハッ　ハッ　ハッ　ハッ　ハッ！
ま　親父たちは親父たち
俺たちは俺たちだ。
Well, our dads have their thing,
and we have our own thing.
気負ったところで　しかたねえ。
No sense in getting
worked up over this.
そうだよね。
You're right.
《自分じゃ成長したつもりでも→
I think I'm all grown up,
父さんから見たら
私なんて　やっぱり子供なのね》
but I guess in my dad's eyes,
I'm still a just a child.
《俺たちのレベルが　親父たちのレベルに
達してねえのは事実だ。
It's a fact that we haven't
reached our dads' level.
敵のレベルは
もっと上と考えたほうがいい。
We have to think that the enemy
is stronger than them.
となると　今度の大戦は…》
Which means,
this upcoming war is...
《いったい　どんな敵と
戦うことになるんだろう》
I wonder what kind of
enemy we'll face.
フフ…。
下忍の頃からよ　俺たちは
逃げることばっか考えていたよな。
From the time
when we were genin,
all we thought about
was running away.
そうね。　ビビって楽な道を探すのに
一生懸命だったわね。
You're right.
We were always scared and
looked for the easy way out.
う…　うん。
Y-Yeah.
いいように捉えれば
自分たちのことをよく知っていた。
If we put a positive spin on it,
you could say we really
knew ourselves well.
そうだ　俺たちは弱え。
え？
That's right. We're weak!
だからこそ　俺たちは考えてきた。
生きる方法を→
That's why we're always
thinking about how to stay alive,
強え敵に勝てる策を…
最善の手をな。
about all the ways to
beat a stronger enemy,
and about what
the best strategy is.
頼むぜ　いの！　チョウジ！
I'm counting on you, Ino, Choji!
親父たちには
敵わねえかもしれねえが→
We may not match up to our dads,
but we won't be going to war alone!
俺たちだけで
戦争に行くわけじゃねえ。
俺たちのできる仕事を
きっちり　こなしていこうぜ。
So let's do what we can,
in the best way possible!
今の自分の全力を
出すしかないものね。
The only thing we can do is to do
our best as the people we are now.
《これまでだって→
Until now, we've stayed together
and done all right.
みんなと一緒なら
大丈夫だったんだ。
今度の戦争だって…》
So even with this next war...
きっと　大丈夫だよね？
We'll be okay, right?
あ？　あぁ…　おぅ。
What? Y-Yeah.
大丈夫　大丈夫！　さぁ　みんな
気合いを入れて　いくわよ！
We'll be fine, just fine!
Okay, guys,
let's get into the spirit!
Let's go!
（みんな）おぉ！
– Right!
♪～
fight!!
furishiboru dake sa saigo no itteki mo
I'm going to squeeze it down to the last drop
muda ni dekinaikara now is the time to go
Because I can't waste any of it, Now is the time to go
ikudo tsuma tsukimi to egaita yume wa
The dream that I created many times with you
ima koe kuma atte munune o sasu
I can now put it to words and it pierces my heart
it's not crazy
fight and fight, try and try for you
forever
kimi wa hitori janai
You are not alone
namida koete
Get over the tears
kimi to susunde ikou
I'll keep moving forward with you
nani mo kowaku narute na ii na
I'm not afraid of anything
this is the place to try
soshite bokura kitto tsunaida te o
I'm sure we'll never let go
kesshite hanasanaide asu e kakeru
Of each other's hands as we head for tomorrow
let's sing loudly
we are the one for the future
Next Episode
Damn it, what a horrible morning!
My dreams were bad,
and everyone is saying Naruto this, Naruto that.
That can't be helped.
Naruto is the village hero right now.
When we were kids he was the worst in our class.
During the Chunin exam, if it weren't for his fart, I would've...
（美空）皆様
おかわりございませんか？
There are no "ifs" in battle. That's because...
You're so annoying! Just you watch!
I'll catch up to him!
美空ひばりです。
では　最後まで
ごゆっくりお楽しみください。
Next time on Naruto Shippuden: "Kiba's Determination"
Kiba's Determination
I won't be left behind!
（宮本）『木曜８時のコンサート
名曲！　にっぽんの歌』。